<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A glasse for housholders wherin thei maye se, bothe howe to rule theim selfes [and] ordre their housholde verye godly and fruytfull.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1542</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 88 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 60 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01782</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11917</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109863</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99845506</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99845506</idno>
            <idno type="VID">10411</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01782)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 10411)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 67:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A glasse for housholders wherin thei maye se, bothe howe to rule theim selfes [and] ordre their housholde verye godly and fruytfull.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[120] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>In officina Richardi Graftoni,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1542.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At foot of title page: Cum priuilegio ad imprimendum solum.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a-g h⁴ (h4 is blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Households --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:10411:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:10411:1"/>
            <p>¶ A glaſſe for houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders, wherin thei maye ſe, bothe howe to rule theim ſelfes &amp; ordre their houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye Godly and fruytfull.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> LONDINI. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> 
               <hi>In officina Richardi Graftoni.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1542.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cum priuilegio ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſolum.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:10411:2"/>
            <head>To the reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this ſmall treatyſe is ſet foorth moſte wholſome councell, fyrſte beyng a young man &amp; vnmaried howe that ye ſhould behaue your ſelfe, after that beyng a maried manne and an houſholder, howe ye ſhoulde bothe rule youre ſelfe and ordre your houſtolde, with alſo an exhortacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and councell what trade and ſorte your occupyeng ſhould bee, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> is to ſay, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> it may be ſpecially for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wealth of the realme that ye are of, and alſo benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial and profitable to your ſelfe, with many other good and wholſome leſſone and coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelles, whiche whoſoeuer folowe, ſhall not only liue here a lyfe profitable both for hym ſelfe and all other menne, but alſo after this life ſhalbe rewarded with that croune and bliſſe, that God the father for Chriſt his ſonnes ſake hath promyſed to theim that are his. *</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:10411:2"/>
            <head>A glaſſe for houſholders.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y entierly beloued the begynnyng of wyſedom is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> loue and feare God, for it cauſeth a manne to withdrawe hym ſelf from doo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng eiuill &amp; maketh hym to dooe good, it is not ynough (my fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de) for to forbeare euil dooinges, but you and I and euery Chriſtyan ought to dooe good, that is to ſaie perfightly to beleue in God, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our ſelfes wholy vnto hym, &amp; to thynke verely then that he will not forſake vs but tenderly will prouide for vs all thynges neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for this life, and will defende vs in all aduerſities, he will geue vs ſtrength to reſiſt his aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and oures in his cauſe, &amp; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this he wyll doubtles make vs ryghteouſe, good, and bleſſed
<pb facs="tcp:10411:3"/> he will remitte and forgeue our ſinnes, he will make vs the heires of his kyngdom and geue vs the life euerlaſtyng. And all theſe he wyll dooe of his mere goodneſſe, of his mere grace and mercy, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe Ieſus Chriſt our Lord our redemer and ſauiour, by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> woorke of the holy goſte. And that for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we beleue in hym, becauſe we be delighted in his lawes and loue his woorde. And becauſe we dooe confeſſe our ſelues to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure and of a corrupte nature, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyrme, feble and weake, &amp; of our ſelues apte to do nothyng which is good in his ſight, but alwayes readye to fall into eternal damp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacion, full of vayne glorye and ypocriſie, vile, wretched, ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and inconſtaunte. And acknowe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgyng ſo his goodneſſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb facs="tcp:10411:3"/> hym we coulde not ſomuche as to thynke one good thought, wherfore, whatſoeuer good tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ught commeth into our myndes, &amp; therafter we ſpeake or woorke it commeth of hym, wherfore we are churliſhe and vnkynde yf we geue not alwayes thankes and prayſes therfore to hym, whyche thynge of dutie we ought to dooe ſithe that all oure good woorkes come of hym, and except thei cam of hym, thei were not good. Let vs then of, and vpon faythe in hym, &amp; onely to glorifie him, dooe good dedes with ſuche goodes &amp; ryches as he hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they bee inwarde riches or outwarde, that is, ghoſtely dedes of mercye or bodelye. And becauſe you ought to make a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conyng to God, for theſe worldly thynges
<pb facs="tcp:10411:4"/> ſhalbe when the ſame ſhal receyue you agayn when ye ſhall die. And thynke that y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> tyme therof might be aſwell this daye as to morowe or the nexte daye. Remembre that it is harde for a riche man to bee a good ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> truthe ſaith that it is more eaſyer for a Camel to crepe through the eye of a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, then for a ryche man to entre into the kyngdome of heauen. And playnly, withoute excepcion true it is, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſaynt Iherome ſayeth whiche ſayeth, that a richeman is eyther vniuſt hymſelfe, or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heire of an vniuſte man. Greate riches can neyther be eyther gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or els kepte without ſynne. Ye muſte re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre &amp; thinke, of how muche bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter ryches thei do robbe you. For they pull away from you the loue of God. Therfore couetouſnes is
<pb facs="tcp:10411:4"/> called ydolatrye of Paule. And Chriſte ſayeth you cannot ſerue God and Mammon. Mammon is y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> deuel, which te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pteth &amp; ſtyreth to coueteouſneſſe. Therefore yf you haue worldlye goodes, ſerue theim not, let not them haue your mynde vndre their ſubieccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But be you a maiſter ouer theim. And remembre y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> you ought to bee the ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is as a ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to vſe theſe riches to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> glorie and prayſe of God the geuer, leaſte you be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dempned of hym as an euel ſeruaunt, not regardyng his maiſters will &amp; pleaſure. Thynke that whoſoeuer be ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geled muche with this world or worldly riches hateth the veraye ſmell and taſte of vertue. And whoſoeuer ſetteth his mynde vpon golde, and hath his affeccion and deſire therunto
<pb facs="tcp:10411:5"/> hateth all honeſt ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, his herte ſhall neuer be quieted with it, but alwayes in trouble, vpon hope to get, or feare to leſe. A couetouſe perſone cannot be ſatiſfyed with golde. The herte of man is ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellente a thing, that all the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures in the worlde cannot fulfill it. (I meane the deſires of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> herte) he only that made it, maye fulfyll and ſatiſfye it &amp; none other thing And he deſireth nothinge elles of man, but that he may dwel in his herte. And where as Mammon is, there wyll not he dwell.</p>
            <p>Therfore yf you will receiue this gifte, expel Mammon, and thruſt hym oute of dores. For Chriſte hathe with no vice leſſe acquayn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce (thoughe he loue none at all) then with couetiſe, wherfore if you ſtudye to pleaſe Chriſte, and
<pb facs="tcp:10411:5"/> come into his fauoure, you muſte geue vp Mammon, and baniſhe hym oute of the coaſtes of youre breſte. For Chriſt and Mammon dwelleth not in one and the ſame place. Bewiſe therfore howe you ſet youre hert to rycheſſe, certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly yf you ſet youre herte to theim, you ſhall euer be poore and voyd of trewe rycheſſe. He that coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth nothyng, is riche and hathe ynoughe. Yf you haue worldly goodes, know of whom you haue receiued theim. And to the geuer be not vnkinde, but haue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to do good, and to be good w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> theim. Let not theim make you worſe by i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ordinate loue. Though you had theim not, yet moughte you do good. For doing good co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> affeccion of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> mind. As yf you had nothing to helpe your
<pb facs="tcp:10411:6"/> chriſten brother, but a cup of cold water. Or if you haue not y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, yet hauyng a piteful and a mercyful mynde, with a good wyll to geue yf you had it, it ſhalbe acceptable afore God. If it be moued of chry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten loue, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> neceſſitee, pouerte infirmytee, calamitee, &amp; wretched<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp; the aduerſyte of my neigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bour. And in theſe thynges, accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ding to my power I do helpe him as I wolde that he ſhoulde helpe me yf I were in lyke condicyon, (as ſayth ſaincte Paule.) Let vs<note place="margin">Gala. vi.</note> worke good to all perſonnes, but ſpecially vnto them that be of the houſholde of faith. And lyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſe, ſaincte Paule to Timothe.<note place="margin">1. Timo. vi.</note> Charge the ryche menne of this worlde to doo good workes, that they maye be ryche in goodneſſe, that thei may gladly reparte their
<pb facs="tcp:10411:6"/> goodes, that they be curteouſe &amp; lyberall.</p>
            <p>Nowe then doyng good conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth<note place="margin">Dooyng good, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiſteth in ii. thynges.</note> in two thynges. The one y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> with lyuyng well and verteouſly you dooe good to your ſelfe. And the other to the poore, with repar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyng your ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with a good will vnto theim. Alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they lacke not your good counſayl whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you maye helpe theim therwith. This firſt maner of doyng good, euery man maye haue and exercyſe. For euery man that wyll deſyre, ſeke or aſke the grace of God maye lyue well and vertuouſly. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde onely vſe they, to whom is geuen by God a charytable mynde to gather worldelye ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce. And theſe perſons inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſantely or contynually wyth thys mynde vſeth this doyng good as
<pb facs="tcp:10411:7"/> longe as god ſendeth theim wher with, thinking that they haue the goodes of hym therfore, that is, that they theim ſelues ſhuld take therof to ſatiſfye their neceſſite or nede, and the reſte to imparte to the poore and nedy. And by this they doo trewely worſhippe God, and the Images of God, and the lykeneſſe of God is ſigned vpon theim that thus dooe. For the per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſone that hathe a full deſire to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe goodly counſailes in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, hath not only the Image of God printed in his ſoule, but alſo the lykeneſſe of God, other deed Images hath nothing commune with theſe Images but onely the ſhadowe, wherfore they might be called better tokens or ſignes of remembraunce.</p>
            <p>Yf we doo thus vpon liuely faith
<pb facs="tcp:10411:7"/> we do not only quicken the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of God: but we oure ſelues, throughe this godly deſyre, do re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the ſimilytude or likeneſſe of God. To helpe other for Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes loue in their nedes, infirmy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees, wretchedneſſe, or to haue a prompte wyll and deſyre to helpe are good dedes and godlye.</p>
            <p>Wherfore the doers of ſuche, can not but be godlye and holye, and to bee ſhorte, lyke vnto Chriſte, which is God.</p>
            <p>This my beloued, I praye you beare in mynde that you do good vnto other with youre worldely ſubſtaunce, and counſayle. And not onely that, but haue a wyll and a feruente deſyre to profyte, many moo then you be able, with worde and dede.</p>
            <p>This aboue al thinges I exhorte
<pb facs="tcp:10411:8"/> you to folowe, that you firſte pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyte your ſelfe, with the firſte ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of doing good, that is to liue well and vertuouſly, as it becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth euery chryſten manne. And God ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng wherwith, you ſhuld vſe the ſeconde maner of doynge good, and that you put it in dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly experience. And ſo doyng, you your ſelfe ſhal not only be ſure to haue of God euerlaſtyng lyfe for your rewarde: but in this life alſo you maye bee aſſured (if you ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtly beleue) not to lacke ſuche thinges as are neceſſary for this preſente lyfe. And beſydes this, with this your good conuerſacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, you ſhall purchaſe a ſure in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herytaunce for youre chyldren. For God neuer ſuffereth the ſede of the iuſte perſonne, for lacke to ſeke his breade.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:10411:8"/>
            <p>For becauſe this tranſitorie or temporal goodes are corruptible &amp; maye decaye, it is to be thought that feare dothe poſſeſſe thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſones whiche haue ſuche in mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate loue towardes theim, that they cannot wel vſe theim. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore to auoyde this peryll, yf God ſende you riches, neuer ſette your mynde or affection on theim. But by &amp; by, with the ſame liberalite that God ſendeth theim, begyn, begynne I ſaye and feare not of lacke, auenture vpon it to diſpoſe and to vſe theim well. Be not like the toade, whiche hath nothynge els vnder hym but earth, and yet he frayeth to ſpende of it, leaſt the earth would fayle hym. Thus I ſaye, not to diſſuade you from laboure to gette goodes by good wayes and all honeſt diligence, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:10411:9"/> by all lawful meanes, for the vice of coueteouſneſſe ſtandeth not in a meaſurable and honeſte deſyre to gette and procure for worldlye thinges, for yf a manne haue this deſyre wythoute inordinate loue towardes hym ſelfe, or vniuſtelye to prouoke hys kynſfolkes or frendes, but deſyreth to vſe theim well to the glorye of God as is aboue ſayde, it is not reprouable. But the roote and croppe of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueteouſneſſe ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth in the harde retencion or kepynge of worldlye goodes, and poſſeſſynge theim, not to reparte with others, nor to take the good vſe of theim, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roughe a diſordinate loue towar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des theim. Wherfore, not ſettyng youre affectionate loue or delyte vpon ryches, ye maye laboure to gette riches and haue theim. But
<pb facs="tcp:10411:9"/> ſee that they haue not you. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure to gette theim wyth the loue and feare ot God. And then I doubte not, but ye wyll ſo vſe theim (hauynge a loue to God a boue ryches,) that when pitee or godlye loue ſhall moue you, ye wyll not ſtycke, doubte nor, feare to vſe of youre goodes to honour God. Suche as laboure to gette goodes after this maner awyſe, will not ſpende theim euill. To deſyre to gette and haue goodes, maye not be euell, yf ſo be you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre, more feruently the vertue of lyberalytee or contempte of theim (as touchyng your ſynguler com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>modytee) to deſyre any thynge to profyte many without carnal af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection is good. He that deſyreth for ryches purelye, foloweth not theym wyth loue: But who is he,
<pb facs="tcp:10411:10"/> and we wyll prayſe hym? Ye muſt euer haue Chriſtes worde in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce: It is harde for him that hath riches to entre into the kyngdome of heauen. Wherfore ye cannot well poſſeſſe ryches (except ye be ſo ſtrong and ſtable in faythe, that you eſteme theim of a ſmall value,) that ye woulde alwayes for Chriſt be contente to leue theim. Fynallye, yf you can poſſeſſe theim, and not be poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of theim: deſyre and laboure to haue theim. Wherfore in all thynges that you dooe as concer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyng your conuerſacion and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupyenge, let this bee a generall rule for you, that is to ſaye: The commaundement of the lawe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall, whiche is, to dooe as you woulde bee dooen to.</p>
            <p>If then you occupie buiynge
<pb facs="tcp:10411:10"/> and ſellynge, I deſyre you to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre this lawe, that whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer any perſone for neceſſitee or nede ſelleth to you any thyng, or alſo for his greate neede woulde buy any thynge of you, inconty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentlye I woulde youre ſelfe to thynke in mynde to bee the ſame perſone whiche with greate nede or neceſſitee buyeth or ſelleth with you, and to conſydre howe you would bee entreated in the ſame cauſe, ſo intreate hym as well in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pryces as choyſe of the ware, as well in the paymente as in any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thyng therunto belongynge. I would you woulde conſidre the gaynes or loſſes of hym that you bargayne with, as your owne, all though parauenture ſome, yea a greate many would iudge, vſyng byeng and ſellyng after this ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner
<pb facs="tcp:10411:11"/> of wyſe, youre gaynes would bee lytle or farre leſſe, then it myght be.</p>
            <p>If you vſed to buy for the leaſt and ſell for the mooſte ye can, as the commen vſe is, thoughe it were ſo (whiche in dede is not) yet a lytle well gotten to a Chriſtyan ſhuld be rekened more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a great deale otherwyſe, It abydeth bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wyth hys owner. And maketh hym to lyue the more merelyer, his conſcyence beyng cleane and voyde of pryckes, whyche theſe thorny ryches are wonte to faſten in a mannes breſte. And beſydes this, the gaynes ſhalbe the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whatſoeuer the worlde thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth. For buiynge and ſellynge wyth ſome lyberalytee, ye ſhall ſell and buy muche more, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tener
<pb facs="tcp:10411:11"/> then other that bee extreme or harde, and wyll haue the vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termooſte of theyr wares. The often gayne then, thoughe at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye tyme were but lytle, maye mounte anone to greater gaynes then otherwyſe.</p>
            <p>Alſo by this maner of dealyng ye ſhall auoyde euell debtes and ſhrewde paymentes, for they that buye wyth gayne dooe ſeldome paye euill. For euyll debtores and frowarde paymentes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth mooſte commenly eyther of eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll wares ſolde for good, other of ouer greate pryce charged in the ware.</p>
            <p>Alſo by thys maner of dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynge, you ſhall alwayſe treate wyth loue and pleaſure, of all that you haue to dooe wyth,
<pb facs="tcp:10411:12"/> and lyue withoute variaunce, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates or plees. Whiche, of all thynges oughte to bee excheiued and auoyded. Wherfore my lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge frende, I praye you to fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe this ordre in buiyng and ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynge, for then that, whiche you gette ſhalbe well gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute charge of conſcyence, and doubtles your gaynes ſhalbe the more, and all with pleaſure, loue and quietnes.</p>
            <p>To commen farther of buiyng and ſellynge of marchaundiſe, you ſhall perceyue that the right office of a true marchaunt, is to prouyde and brynge to lande or place where he is, all ſuche wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, as are ſcarce and vnplenty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyfull in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayde place, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarye for the wealthe of the lande
<pb facs="tcp:10411:12"/> And alſo to carye and ſende oute all ſuche wares as are ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe and dooe habounde in the places where he is, into places where is ſcarceneſſe or lacke of theim. As here in Englande, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe clothe, tynne and leade, be plenteouſe, theſe wares ye maye ſende hence, and not corne, or thin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges pertaini<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to vitailes, though here were greate haboundaunce. It can not be but hurtfull to lade any oute of the lande. And the retourne of theſe warys <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ether, ſhould be in yron, ſtele, and other metallis, whiche we haue nede of Alſo in Woade, Alam, Madder, and ſuche other lyke thynges ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for oure clothe makyng. And as for apples, cheries, gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and onions, with other fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, wynes, ſpicis, ſylke, clothe of
<pb facs="tcp:10411:13"/> golde and other lyke, myghte be lefte very well. For we might liue withoute theſe marchaundizes, for thei do rather prouoke men to vices then to temporate liuinge, and good and honeſte, ſobre and chaſte behauoure. And with theſe marchaundize, I mighte couple furres of greate prices, and very fine clothe, for theſe are euen ſo ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perfluouſe as the other, of meane prices are neceſſary, and behoua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Theſe maye be named for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, for to name all kindes of marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dizes neceſſarie and not neceſſarie, profytable, and vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, were to muche.</p>
            <p>This oughte to be taken hede of, that it is the offyce of a good mar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>chaunte to ſende oute of the coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tree, the thinges which are moſte ſuperfluouſe, and to bring thither
<pb facs="tcp:10411:13"/> thinges moſte neceſſarye. And ſo ſhall his gaynes be the more, and better gotten, bicauſe he doeth it to helpe the neceſſyte of his neigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>boures.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ Howe ye oughte to be conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunte with youre elders.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S touchyng your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſacion with your el<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (I praye you) in much reuerence be gentle and louing to youre e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualles. And in no wiſe, deſpice youre inferiors. Alſo reuerence all deuoute perſones, in the choiſe of theim haue none affeccyon to the cloke or crowne nor other ſuch outward tokens only. But where
<pb facs="tcp:10411:14"/> you perceyue example of vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe liuing, pure, chaſte, &amp; cleane in worde and dede. Suche a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone haue in honoure and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, be he man or woman. And thynke that then you do honoure the Image and very lykeneſſe of God, yea God in his image, what garment ſoeuer he wareth. Alſo ſe (I praye you) that you be not full of wordes, remembring this ſayeng of the wyſe manne.</p>
               <p>* That I haue ſpoken, I repente then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge.</p>
               <p>But I neuer repented, that I helde my tongue.</p>
               <p>If the herte be redy to moue the tongue to ſpeake y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> you wold not Saye to youre tongue. Tongue whyther goeſt thou? Fle frome menne full of wordes, and medle not muche with theim, bicauſe ſin wyll be where muche babling is.
<pb facs="tcp:10411:14"/> Fle alſo the company of whiſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and lyers, yf youre preſence can not refourme theim. For they muſt nedes engender anger, and the indignacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God. And ſuch as be the louers of God, loue the truthe in all thinges, ſo y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> in ſporte nor in earneſte it appere that you delight to ſaye nor heare any lyes or thinges ſounding therunto. Alſo in doyng benefytes or good dedes to other, loue promptneſſe, quickeneſſe and haſte. For it is twiſe geuen, the whiche is gladly and redely geuen. Be not haſtye or roughe in denieng any honeſt thyng that is aſked of you, yf ye canne do it. For it is conuenient that whome you can not helpe in dedes, at leeſt with youre good worde you ſo dyſpatche him, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he may perceiue, your wil to be good</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10411:15"/>
               <p>Fraude and deceite you ſhulde not onely auoide and not do, but not once conſente that any other ſhoulde deceytie or defraude any manne or woman or childe if you maye lette it. Alſo haue no enuye at any mannes proſperytee, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yet be gladde of any mannes aduerſytee. Ponder the gaynes and loſſes of youre neyghbours, to be gladde and ſorye for theim, like as you wolde of youre owne that they maye waye youres in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame balaunce. Moreouer, ſee that you dooe nothinge in youre houſe, that you wolde not to bee knowen in the market place.</p>
               <p>Thynke that the worſte parte of youre ſeruauntes is the tongue. And thoughe you youre ſelfe (as alwaies ſhould) feare to doo any viciouſe thynge alone, be not yet
<pb facs="tcp:10411:15"/> witneſſe to other of ſuche dedes. For he that holdeth his tongue, &amp; feareth to rebuke ſynne for God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des ſake, he feareth more manne then he loueth God, and loueth neyther of bothe, as he oughte to dooe.</p>
               <p>Beſydes this, if youre goodes encreaſe, you ſhould not only en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in goodneſſe &amp; good dedes to the poore and nedeful perſons but let youre ſeruauntes alſo fele the aduauntage of youre gaines Good reaſon it is, that they that are parteners of the laboures, en<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ioye parte of the profyte. But yf fortune looke ſowerlye vpon you and withdrawe proſperouſe ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſyon frome you, lette theim ſee youre ſayles borne after the blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wynge of the wynde. Alſo flee plees and debates, all contency<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:10411:16"/> and ſtrife, though youre cauſe ſeme neuer ſo good. If it be a mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ney mater, that thinke very gay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, what ſoeuer of ſtrife you loſe with money. For loſſe of brawling and ſtrife with money, maye well be rekened gaynes to theim that loue God, peace, and charytee, and contempne money for Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes cauſe, leaue ſtrife to theym y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> loue more money then peace or charyte. For in the lawe, beſides y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you ſhal ſtand in dought to haue iuſtice though your mater be iuſt yet the tediouſneſſe or werineſſe, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> anger and buſyneſſe to folowe it, the laboure, vexacion, the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyng attendaunce, the diſdayne &amp; heuy mindes of the contrary par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and all other ſuche inconue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences engendred by plees ſhuld be exchewed what ſoeuer it coſte.
<pb facs="tcp:10411:16"/> And to auoyde this, haue you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes (yf you dooe by me) a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecte and a good iudgemente of the perſones with whome you en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termedle. And where you maye perceaue one that delighteth and vſeth plees, varyau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or wrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynges, beware that ye contracte not with hym in any wyſe, what gaynes ſoueuer ye might ſuppoſe to folowe of his contraction.</p>
               <p>Encreaſe diligently the noum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre of your fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des, and kepe theyr frendſhippe. And for a iuſte cauſe you maye deuide a ſymuled fre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de from your conuerſacion or inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medlyng. But ſee that ye appeare not ſodenlye to bee his contrarye let hym learne by euidente woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des or tokens that you leaue one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye hys euell behaueoure or vice, And becauſe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he hym ſelf wil not
<pb facs="tcp:10411:17"/> leaue it, you maye not choſe but leaue hym. And alſo better it is, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> by a lytle &amp; a lytle you leaue your frendſhip, then ſodenly to breake it. So ſhall he learne that you for ſake his ſymuled frendſhip, &amp; his noughtye condicions rather then hym, for a ſymuled frend is worſe then an open enemye. Amongeſte your louers choſe ſome of the beſt and moſte faythfulleſt, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your right iudgement perceyueth to be treweſt, moſte faythfull and ſted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſte, to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye maye ſhewe your counſell and ſecretes. As for to fynde many to who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a man maye entierly and vndoubtedly truſt, is very harde. I would wyſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he you to haue no ſecretes, which ſhould be dau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gerous or perylous to you though thei were openly knowne to all menne. Yet if you finde one
<pb facs="tcp:10411:17"/> or two of ſuche clere &amp; pure fayth that ye maye truſte aſwel as your ſelfe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wyll take euery thyng well and in the beſte parte, thoughe it ſhoulde ſeme to many otherwyſe, loue hym as your ſoule. Further<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more, though the opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men people is ſeldome approued to be good, yet it is no wyſedome alwayes to ſaye agaynſte it. But it ſhall dooe well to go the hyghe waye as other do, thoughe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> path be many tymes better. The pathe and rightwaye of the Goſpell or worde of God, in no condicion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng lefte or forſaken. Alſo flee all flaterers, vayne boaſters &amp; pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers of your goodneſſe or vertues let theim ſee ſuche flaterye &amp; ſymu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lacion to be litle pleaſure to you, euen at the fyrſte hearynge, that they ſhewe the countenau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of it.
<pb facs="tcp:10411:18"/> Eſteme not youre dedes by other mennes ſayenges: but entre into your ſelfe, and betwixte the truthe and youre conſcience, ſeke the exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimacion of youre ſelfe. Care not what this or that man doeth ſaie: but what the truth ſayth to youre conſcience, no man but God and you (excepte ye ſhewe any manne) knoweth what youre entente or meanynges are. Wherfore, the truthe in your knowledge ought to make you free, mery, reſtfull, &amp; quiet, agaynſt all quarell pykers or falſe fynders of faultes. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore in all blames or prayſes, flee to conſcience, if amongeſte theſe ſhe ſpeake well Happye are you, mightie &amp; wyſe. For it is as pere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leouſe a thyng to be falſely pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as falſely blamed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10411:18"/>
               <head>¶ The gouernaunce of your ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes and inferiours.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>ROCVRE alwayes to ſubdue theim that are vnder you, rather by loue then w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> feare for he that is feared of many, muſte feare many. And be not with vnkynde wordes and roughe, light to prouoke theim to wrathe. If you youre ſelfe be ſty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to anger, I woulde then that ye woulde ceaſe to ſaye or do any thynge, vntyll your wrathe bee a layde or ſlaked, for there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge well ſayde or done whiche is ſayd or done in a furye. Wrath is an euell maiſtres to gouerne thynges. Putte awaye alſo wyth ſpede all ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kered thoughtes whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out a good reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce of Chriſtes promyſe, maye lyghtlye
<pb facs="tcp:10411:19"/> corrupte youre mynde with inor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynate thoughtes, (I meane in gettyng or kepyng your goodes) hauyng youre mynde faſtened to Chriſtes promyſe with dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowyng, ye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not lacke, wherfore beware of to ſtayte kepyng. And remembre that though ye mighte get al the worldly goodes that be in the worlde in a ſhorte ſpace, yet by death ye might looſe theim in a ſhorter. Thynke that ther is no thynge comparable to a quyete mynde and a reſtefull. That is a contented mynde, whiche feareth no loſſes, nor greatly or gredelye coueteth gaynes. Nothynge is ſo muche to be abhorred as the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliccion of the ſpirite, but as I do counſell you to auoyde theſe pha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſtical and deſpayryng myndes: So I do aduyſe you to auoyde
<pb facs="tcp:10411:19"/> negligence &amp; ſlothe in your buſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, or ouermuch ſlackenes or diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſolucion in not ſauyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which is gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For as great faulte it is to loſe negligently y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> which is gotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as to procure inordinately to get that whiche of right &amp; conſcience ought not to be gotten. With ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt gaynes, be you alwayes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted in all your buiyng &amp; ſellyng ſo that ye hauyng gaynes y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> other partie receaue no loſſe, as is afore ſaid, for ſo your gaynes w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hym, &amp; his w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yours may lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge continue, for he that ſoftely mylketh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cowe bryngeth forth milke, and he that herdelye and ſtraytely wryngeth the tettes bryngeth forth bloode.</p>
               <p>Alſo my dere beloued frende whether you bee maryed, as yet I can not tell redelye, but conſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derynge youre age, compleccion
<pb facs="tcp:10411:20"/> or bodely ſtate and worldlye ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce, I perceaue that ye maye well maynteyne a wyſe, wherfore I do aduyſe you (yf your ghoſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtrengthe be not greatere then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> infyrme &amp; nyce deſyre of fleſhly ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>petites) to take a wife: but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> choiſe of her be not ouer hedlyng haſty, or raſhe. But with good delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion endeuoure your ſelfe to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye. God is well pleaſed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> chaſte maryage &amp; ſobre, which is an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable &amp; holy thyng with hym, and ſore diſpleaſed with whoredo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and adulterye: yea &amp; with dedes of mariage vngodly, abhomyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly &amp; beaſtely vſed. Mariage is a dede whiche you owe to nature, &amp; to your contrey &amp; to God, yf your infyrmyte be ſuche y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ye maye not liue chaſte out of matrimonie, &amp; if alſo youre fruite of matrymony<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10411:20"/> be godly and verteouſlye ducated and broughte forthe in the loue &amp; feare of God. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> choſe a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> In the choyſe of youre wife, haue onely reſpecte to her vertue and honeſtye, whiche forbicauſe peradue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture it cannot be, by and by, or ſone ſene in her. Loke to the ſtocke of the younge braunche, I meane her father: But ſpecially looke vpon the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ners of her mother, for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menly the doughter is manered muche after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mother, yf ſhe be brought vp at home with her parentes, yf in an other place, ioyne her mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers condicyons with her may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and maiſtreſſe, &amp; waie theim in a iuſte paire of balaunce. You may here y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reporte of diſcrete per ſones of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of her gouernours and her. If ſhe haue bene any ſpace of tyme frome her mothers
<pb facs="tcp:10411:21"/> company I wolde you dyd count more vpon the vſe, and good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauioure of her gouernours then her parentes, for good or euel edu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tacion or bringing vp, chaungeth nature. Conſider alſo her age, that ſhe be yonger then you. And of her bewtye y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſhe be in a meane fauoure or bewtifulneſſe. For as it is harde to kepe a fayre and a bewtifull woman chaſte, whome all menne be moſte redy to deſire: So it is truely tediouſe and loth ſome to poſſeſſe an euell fauored woman or vnfruytefull, whome all men dooe abhorre. Yet mary you a wyfe for youre owne ſelfe, and not for other menne. Other men ought not to be delighted in youre wyues outwarde beawtie, nor you in theirs. But thus that you laude God in his creatures,
<pb facs="tcp:10411:21"/> whiche no man dothe by concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence agaynſte his commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement. So that ſhe be of a good name and fame. For it is not y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noughe, that a woman be voide of any euell dede or dedes, but I wolde her to be voyde of all euell ſuſpicion. And thoughe I make no difference of mayde or widowe by Goddes lawe, yet I wolde cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cell you to take a virgyn or mayd whome you maye forme and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructe after youre owne maners And ſhe wyll ſoner apply to your mind, and more entierly loue you then a wydowe. I make no men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of the dowrye. If ſhe bringe any ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, it is not to be refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, if not, ſhe ſhalbe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eſlier gouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned or ruled in exſpences, &amp; lowlier or more obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to ſerue you. And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you mary, I wyl exhorte you
<pb facs="tcp:10411:22"/> to thinke that you entre into reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and that you and your wife ſhould prepare youre ſelues there after. Not to thynke, as many lightly dooe, that mariage is a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to lyue voluptuouſlye, and vnder the tytle of mariage or ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trimony, to fulfyl all their carnal deſires. But thinke you after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde to lyue more ſoberlye and temparatelye, more vertuouſlye, and honeſtly, and to geue mo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamples of good liuing, then you did before, remembring that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trimonye is one of the holyeſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes that God hath ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. And that therfore it ſhoulde be vſed with all honeſtye, deuoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and reuerence. And in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uy duitie of matrimony, I wolde you and youre wife, ſo to diſpoſe you, that in youre bodies were al
<pb facs="tcp:10411:22"/> temparateneſſe and ſoberneſſe, &amp; youre mindes and ſpirytes liſted vp to God, deſiring hym not only of fruite, but of ſuch fruite, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may be apte to his ſeruice. And yf you in this acte be coupled with this minde and deſire, no doubte but God wyll ſende you ſuche maner of fruite as you deſyre. It is a greate beaſtlineſſe, ſeing that all menne deſire to haue chyldren of good diſpoſicion and helthfull in their bodies, alſo with good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinacion, and minde to vertue &amp; goodneſſe: that at the generacion of theim they haue no conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion to prepare theim after theyr deſire. Beleue me chryſten bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that yf they that engender, &amp; conceiue be temperate and ſober in that acte, and haue their helth the childe ſhalbee of a good tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perature
<pb facs="tcp:10411:23"/> in bodye and of a good compleccyon. And yf alſo theyr mindes be lifted vp to God as is aforeſayde, the chylde ſhall alſo haue inclinacyon to vertue and goodneſſe. As the children repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent their fathers likeneſſe or mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the fourme of theyr bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies: Euen ſo their inclinacion of goodneſſe and vertue ſhall repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the fathers and mothers diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſicyon, whiche they had when the chyldren were begoten or en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendered, whiche yf it were not good or godlye, ſo ſhall the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren be dyſpoſed to be all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dayes of their lyfe. All vyces then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounde vnto the chyldren frome the father and mother ſpeciallye, then might the father and mother to be well dyſpoſed in bodye and ſoule, in the acte of generacion, or
<pb facs="tcp:10411:23"/> elles afterwarde it ſhall tourne theim to greate diſpleaſure, in the frowardneſſe of theyr children.</p>
               <p>Wherfore I pray you marke wel this admonicion, and put it well in remembraunce, ſpecially, when you be about ſuch buſineſſe wher vnto be you not drawen, as often as Venus wolde. But when you perceyue helthe, ſobreneſſe, and temperatneſſe both in you and in your wyfe, the loue of God &amp; his honour had in your reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>braunce as is aboueſaid to diſpoſe of your fruite withoute beaſtlineſſe, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che is onely to accompliſhe your owne fleſhly pleaſure. To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude I wolde bothe of you ſhuld beare chaſte Chriſte conceiued in youre breſtys by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hearing or redyng of his holy worde. And folow Mary &amp; Ioſephes matrimony in actes.
<pb facs="tcp:10411:24"/> And if you wolde (as I truſte you wyll) that youre wyfe ſhoulde be cleane alwaies of her liuing from other men. And thoughe ſhe fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe not Maries virginite, yet I wold ſhe endeuored to folowe her ſhame faſtneſſe in matrimonye.</p>
               <p>This will your minde be I truſt that ſhe alwaies ſaye and do that thyng whiche beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth a lauda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble woman or wife to dooe. That ſhe may thus do it, muſte be your diligence to enduce her ſpecially in the begi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning to loue and feare God. But to bring this about, no wordes are ſufficient, no councell or exhortacion, excepte you youre ſelfe ſo liue, that ſhe may perforce folowe youre good exſample, and dooe the ſame. And therfore as I ſaide before, that when you mary you ſhoulde reken that you enter
<pb facs="tcp:10411:24"/> into religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Specially in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynnynge, for where as hytherto any negligence of vertue and of good lyuynge or ſeruice of God y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> was dooe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, was dooen onely to youre owne hurte: From hence forthe the euil example ſhal hurte your wife, your chyldren, &amp; your ſeruauntes, that is to ſaye: all the whole houſholde. In the begyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge therfore, ſpecially ye muſte induce your wife with your good example, in the loue and feare of God, whiche ones graffed or prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted in her mynde, ſhall cauſe that ſhe ſhal ſaye, ne dooe any thynge that afterwarde ſhe ſhall gretly repente. Alſo I doubte not, but ye would gladly that youre wyfe ſhoulde loue you, the meane is to cauſe her ſo to dooe, that ſhe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue playnly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſhe is entierly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loued
<pb facs="tcp:10411:25"/> of you. For whiche it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyſeth not, onelye to wythdrawe your mynde from al other wem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. But that ye muſt alſo, auoide any occaſyon, of whiche might bee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendered euyll ſuſpycion of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinencye. For yf gelouſye entre ones into wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s breſtes, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> roote is ſo vnſauerye and bitter that it cannot chooſe but brynge forth y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> weryſhe and lothſome fruyte of diſcorde, then the whiche there is none ſo greate a poyſon, that cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupteth ſo muche Chriſten folkes but ſpecially the man and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wife. Beſydes this, in your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerſacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with your wyfe, be ye famylyer &amp; louyng, guydyng her therwith to althynges of your mynd by fayre meanes, and not by rygorouſnes crueltie or tyranny. If ſhe be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt &amp; verteous, your worde ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:10411:25"/> ſuffice, yf otherwyſe (whiche God forbyd, leſte ye might be ouerſene in thynges aforeſayde) it maye be done by force moderatly, yet ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle intreatie is better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cruelty, boy ſteoruſnes or ſtripes, except there be ſuche obſtinacie in her whiche ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be helped without enforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and correccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, neuer correcte with ſhamefull rebuke. If there be any ſuch obſtinacie, reaſon you ſo with her, that ſhe may perceaue her faulte and conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pne her ſelfe whiche ſhalbe a good correccion. Menne and wemen are of nature gentyll to be ledde and not to bee drawen, for nature hath made theim wythoute all wepon to vſe crueltee or tyrannye, al other bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, nature hathe armed wyth ſome defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but it bryngeth forth man w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out any weapon, wherfore
<pb facs="tcp:10411:26"/> nature wold ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kynde to be ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tle &amp; peaceable aboue al other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. I would haue your louing conuerſacion and famyliaritee w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your wyfe ſo myxte with honeſtie and ſhame faſtenes, that ſhe in no wyſe perceyue or ſee in you any exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple by which y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> virginal ſhame faſteneſſe whiche ſhe had before youre mariage bee leſſed after it. And this aſwell ſecretlye when you are together in your chaum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre and bedde, as openlye. For where men wyth ſhameful hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynges and vnchaſte woordes, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vnclenlye geſtoures, ſygnes or lookes, prouoke theyr wyues to fleſhly luſte, whom maye they iuſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly blame, yf theyr wyues lyue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſtelye but theimſelues, as the chefe cauſers, for wyth ſuche be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haueoure they make their wyues
<pb facs="tcp:10411:26"/> voyde of all ſhamefaſtnes, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beyng banyſhed &amp; gone, chaſtite maketh haſt after. Wherfore now yf you wyl haue your wife chaſte ſhe muſt haue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> example of you, &amp; not onelye that, but ye muſte vſe her with all clenlyneſſe, honeſtye and ſhamefaſtneſſe. And to allure her to loue kyndnes, honeſtie and chaſtenes, you ſhall apparell or clothe her by myne aduyſe ſo that wherſoeuer ſhe beſene, ſhe might bee iudged to bee youre wyfe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng not ſo riche apparell or clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynge to bee iudged ſome mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chauntes wyfe of hier dignitee or ſome greate mannes wyfe of the courte: nor ſo poorely, that you be yng of ſome worldlye ſubſtaunce ſhe might bee iudged to bee ſome poore labouryng mans wyfe, let her go after the ſame ſorte, condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion
<pb facs="tcp:10411:27"/> or eſtate that ye are of or ſhal be of. For the whiche equalitee it ſhalbe good that ye bothe be clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed of one pece of cloth. Let your garmentes be of the moſte honeſt facion, leauynge iagges and new inuencio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s without profyte or eaſe to the bodye, to therin that thynke onely gaye thynges to be good, &amp; pleaſure better then profyte. Alſo herein auoyde all occaſyons to be enuighed as nye as ye maye, or any occaſion where thorough an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gre or diſcorde mighte ryſe, &amp; not onely in this thynge, but in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with your wyfe. But ſpecy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally in the begynnyng of your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſacion, for if before one knowe well the condicions or maners of the other, and alſo before that any perfyght loue bee well rooted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twyxte you, any dyſcenſion or
<pb facs="tcp:10411:27"/> wrangelyng aryſe, it wylbe harde afterwarde to be turned into a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>formyte or an vnyte of lyuynge quyetlye together. Specially, yf in ſuche angre, paſſe any myſche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous wordes or ſtyngyng or prickynge wordes or ſtrypes, loue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde is to bee deſpayred al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſte for euer, whiche diſſencion or wrangelyng, though it happen afterwardes that y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> loue betwi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>te you be wel rooted &amp; eſtabliſhed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> one knoweth wel the other, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gre or diſcorde can be ſo gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e, but that ſone you ſhoulde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne agayne into grace and fauoure, into peace and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10411:28"/>
               <head>¶ The gouernynge of a houſholde</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LSO, the charge of the gouernau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> houſe, ye maye in maner geue wholly to youre wyfe, &amp; as ye would y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſhe ſhould not muche entermedle in youre marchau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſe or buſynes whiche is done out of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> houſe or out of her roome: So it is not ſemyng that you great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buſye youre ſelfe in thynges ol the houſe longyng to her charge as many woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly men do, whiche wyllynglye withoute comelynes come vnder the ſubieccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of theyr wyues. And ioyne to this forſaid charge of the houſe, ſome other buſyneſſe and laboure mete for her, ſo that ſhe maye alwayes be occupied &amp; neuer ydell. Many other thynges myght be ſayde as
<pb facs="tcp:10411:28"/> concerning the conuerſacyon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixe the huſbande and the wyfe, whiche nowe of purpoſe I leaue to ſpeake of, leſte I ſhoulde be te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diouſe to you in reading my ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple councelles. Experience hathe and maye inſtructe you farre bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then my wytte can expreſſe, yet ſomwhat I wyl ſaye more as con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cerning youre chyldren.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>¶ As concerning children.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Irſt, God ſending you<note place="margin">It is again nature, tha wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhal not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> their owne children.</note> children. Se that none other woman nurſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> than youre owne wyfe. It is a greate vncomlyneſſe and inconuenience, yea I ſaye cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that comenly is vſed among menne and women, I dooe not ſaye beaſtlineſſe, for that they put
<pb facs="tcp:10411:29"/> forth their yonge children to nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, yea and ſom men and wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyll caſte theyr chyldren oute of doores within a. iii. or fouredaies after that it is borne, to a ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to noriſhe it. It is to be won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered verely what confydence the mother of the childre hathe, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally foraſmuche as ſhe thynkety that a ſtraunge woman wyll ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the laboure which is requiſite in the nurſſing of the child, when ſhe that is naturall mother refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth it. They wyll anon ſaye, that for money a ſtraunger wyll do it well and conueniently, ſo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> theyr chylde ſhalbe well noryſhed and brought home faire and fatte. I ſaye though it be faire &amp; fatte, yet it is not ſo naturallye fayre &amp; fat, as though his owne mother had noriſhed him. And that it is faire
<pb facs="tcp:10411:29"/> and fatte, it is no more thanke to the mother the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to a Iewe, willing a chriſtian chylde to be noryſhed, for his fantaſticall loue, and ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore geueth money haboundaunt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to ſome woman, that wolde not be ſene to receyue his money in vayne, but for his money ſhe ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth her diligent laboure. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> the childe is fayre and fatte, it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth more of the loue of the norſe that ſhe hath to the chylde within litell tyme after that ſhe hath ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it her milke, which cauſeth her to ſette leſſe of the laboure, or paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth more vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> child then vpon the money. But who wyll doubte but the chyld ſhuld be more helth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful a more te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>perat in body if it had ſucked, his natural lyquore, wher w<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he was noriſhed i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his mothers wo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be. Who may thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nature
<pb facs="tcp:10411:30"/> not doo muche more to the helthe and good diſpoſicyon of the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des bodie then money can doo, or euer ſhalbe able to dooe? Verely it is not like, but the chylde ſhuld be the helthyer not onely in his in fancye, but all dayes of his lyfe afterwarde, yf the mother wolde playe the mother in noriſhing the childe. Once in the beginninge, they put the chylde in ieopardy of his lyfe, in taking hym from his naturall milke wherwith he was noriſhed in his mothers wombe. And beſides that, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> mother hathe neuer ſo perfyghte loue to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> child whiche an other woman noryſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth, as if ſhe noriſhed it her ſelfe for whileſt ſhe noriſheth it not, ſhe remaineth but halfe a mother, for the offyce of an whole &amp; parfyght mother is, to beare chyldren and
<pb facs="tcp:10411:30"/> noriſhe them or bring theim forth. Nowe ſhe reparteth the one parte with y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> norſe. And ſo alſo in loue ſhe remayneth but half a mother. They wil ſaye that their loue can not be diminiſhed towardes their children though other women no riſhe them, but it is not ſo. For thoughe noriſhing of children be laborious and peynfull, yet it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendreth muche loue betwixte the nurſe and the chylde. This loue then whiche is wonte to be engen dered by noriſhing the chylde, is loſte of the naturall mother tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardes the chylde, and is added to the noryſhe, wherfore the mother hath loſt halfe her loue towardes the childe, and the norſe hath and ſhall fynde it. Likewiſe wyll the childe deuide his loue into. ii. par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes. The one parte to his mother
<pb facs="tcp:10411:31"/> bearing hym, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> other to his nurſe or halfe mother feadyng and brin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ging him forth. And beſides this yf the mother that bare the chyld had noryſhed it alſo, the loue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> father wold had bene much more to the chylde, becauſe of the nory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of it in his preſence. And of this ſpringeth the litle loue or vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naturall loue that menne haue to theyr chyldren, ſpeciallye in this realme. Afterwardes when y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> child is a. xii. monethes or two yeres of age, it is brought home from no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing, and is brought vp in the houſe vntyll it be. xii. or. xiii. yeres olde, with litell difference as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his profyte betwene hym and the ſeruaunt. And being of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> age rude and vnlearned, becauſe they theim ſelues wolde not take paines to induce hym to vertue &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:10411:31"/> learninge or crafte, they thruſte hym out of dores againe to may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to ſerue withoute any grete conſideracyon, whether the perſo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes be of good and honeſt diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicyon whiche ſhall receyue hym, yea or whyther they wyll profyte greately the chylde to vertue and honeſtye, oute of dores they caſte hym as before at noriſhyng. If his fortune be to meete w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a good mayſter, to whome he might reſte more bound then to his father or mother, happy is he, by his good mayſter he learneth to helpe hym ſelfe, whiche he dyd not of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and mother, many fathers &amp; mothers ar not ſtudiouſe to helpe theyr chyldren to vertue or lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge, becauſe they loue money more then theyr chyldren.</p>
               <p>And bycauſe they ſo dooe, they
<pb facs="tcp:10411:32"/> departe nothing of it to their chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren in theyr lyfe. But yf hys chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce be not to meete w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a good maiſter, he is tangled and corrup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted with ſuche vyces, whiche in youth commonly haue domyny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and rule, &amp; gooe not forwarde to vertue and honeſtye: where as a good father ſhulde then receiue his chylde, and by fayre meanes and fatherly councell amend him and comforte hym in goodneſſe, and geue hym ſome of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des to ſocoure him. But the vſe is cleane contrary, for then he deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> entering into his houſe then he wyll not name hym, nor knowe hym for his ſonne or child denyeth him all fauoure to cauſe hym diſpaire, and caſte away the whole purpoſe to lyue honeſtlie &amp; trewely. And ſo deſperate and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecte
<pb facs="tcp:10411:32"/> abſenteth hym ſelfe from his father and mother, and coupleth hym ſelfe with light wanton, vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and naughtye companye, &amp; is made one of theim, where y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whiche in the begynnynge myght eaſely haue be ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded are encreaſed &amp; growen vncorrygy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and that, becauſe the father &amp; mother dooe not gracyouſly loue theyr child. If they dyd loue their chyldren to God wardes, that is to ſaye, to brynge theim forthe in the lawes of God, and wold that they ſhulde loue and drede God. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> would they, beyng of power thereto put theim to lernynge in theyr tendre age, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyderyng this commen prouerbe:</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>He that in youth no vertue wyll vſe,</l>
                  <l>In age all honoure ſhall hym refuſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Alſo the ſaiynge of Salomon:
<pb facs="tcp:10411:33"/> Looke what waye a younge man or woman taketh in hys tendre age, from that he wyl not departe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is old. Alſo experie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſhew eth that youth wyl lightly folowe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> inſtruccio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of theyr elders. The younge cocke croweth like as he heareth the olde. And loke howe a young twygge of an orcheyarde is bowed ſo he groweth forthe, yf he be ſtayed to growe vp ryghte, ſo it groweth, and is bothe profy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and pleaſaunte. If it growe otherwyſe I cannot tell whereto it is profytable, but to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fyre. Like wyſe maye be ſayd of young chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but the faulte is not in the chyldren, but in the elders or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and mothers. The chylde Ieſus dyd growe and was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted in ſpiryte ful of wyſdome &amp; the grace of God was wyth hym,
<pb facs="tcp:10411:33"/> that is to ſaye: he was a notable good chylde, and ſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a younge man, he grewe to an exceadynge wyſe &amp; verteous man. It is mete that ſuche as be Chriſten chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould be brought vp after thex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of Chriſte. He did growe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was comforted by the ſpyrite and in the ſpirite. Many menne ſuffre theyr chyldren to vſe ryot &amp; be loſt in fleſhely pleaſures, nor do cauſe theim to be induced to fayth &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſte lyuyng, by the word of God, Chriſt dyd growe and encreaſe in wyſedome, many ſuffre their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to encreaſe in foliſhnes. And the grace of God was in Chriſte, but thoroughe the faulte of theyr fathers &amp; mothers it taryeth not with ſome children called chriſten chyldren, yet nothyng folowyng Chriſt, or ſmell of hym, becauſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10411:34"/> Chriſt dyd growe in the ſighte of men and dyd appeare whole per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyghte and wonderfull by and by preachyng ſignes and myracles. It is conuenient or ſyttynge that lyke manner of wyſe oure chyldren bee induced and inſtructed to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocion, to vertue, &amp; good lyuynge A man wyll not thynke lyghtlye howe much good lyeth in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> bryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng vp of chyldren. And if there wer not greate vertue and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in it, who myght thynke that God would ſo ſtraytly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde the Iewes y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhould be induced, inſtructed &amp; broughte vp, in the feare of God: verelye he doeth knowe beſte of al, that that thyng wyll not lyghtely be lefte in ryper or ferther age, whyche chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue accuſtomed in their tendre age. The whiche thyng th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:10411:34"/> Latyne Poete expreſſeth &amp; ſayth: So greate a thynge it is to accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome a thynge from tendre age. Wherfore God in Deuteronomy the .vi. chapiter ſayth: Thou ſhalt rolle in thy mynde with thy ſelfe ſuch thynges as I geue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> charge vpon this daye, and thou ſhalte whette theim vpon thy chyldren, ſpeakyng therof to theim when y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> taryeſte at home in thy houſe, or walkeſt on thy iourneye, when y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> goeſt to bedde and ryſeſt their fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If thou leaue theſe thynges in theyr youthe, thou ſhalte haue muche ado to make theim obeye and folowe when they be of a full age and olde. But nowe ye wyll ſay, I am no preacher. Therunto with ſaynt Auguſtyne I anſwere the, Looke what a preacher is in the pulpet, ſuche euery houſhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb facs="tcp:10411:35"/> is in his houſe at home. And likewyſe as it belongeth for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate to make rekenyng &amp; accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt for his whole flocke: So the houſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>holder in the general daye of iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gemente ſhal reken and make ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coumpte for his wife, for his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and for his houſholde.</p>
               <p>Geue ye therfore diligent hede that in this be halfe ye bee not founde negligent, loue your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren after this maner. And when they be of ſome diſcrecio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, let them perceyue your loue in worde and worke. And be not ſo vnkynde as ſome fathers, whiche for the loue of this worldlye ryches and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyſhe pleaſure (whyleſt they lyue) can not fynde in theyr hartes to departe with theim, though they haue receyued it of the hande of God euen for the ſame purpoſe.
<pb facs="tcp:10411:35"/> Wherof procedeth that many ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes for a veray litle anger or di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpleaſure the father doeth wholly diſheryte his ſonne, or at leaſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hym a great parte of his inherytau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ce, wherof alſo procedeth that men can fynde in their hertes many tymes y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> theyr ſeruauntes ſhould be made diſpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſers of theyr goodes or theyr fren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des, rather then theyr children. Al this (as I ſuppoſe) procedeth of none other thyng, but of the lytle loue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they haue to theyr chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: And this litle loue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth of this that the natural mother noriſhed not her owne chylde in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the father.</p>
               <p>Wherfore my dere frende and Chriſten brother let youre owne wyfe noryſhe youre chylde, euen though it ſhoulde ſeame a newe
<pb facs="tcp:10411:36"/> thyng and not vſed. Forſoth God and nature hath not wrought bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes and teates in youre wyfe, yea and mylke, healthe and habylytee in vaine, yf theſe ſhould not ſerue for her owne chyldren. And beſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des this ſhe maye not ryghtly be called a mother fullye and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyghtly afterwardes, of her owne chyldren, beynge but halfe a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. And hereof procedeth alſo the coulde loue and ſmal reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſome childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue in their age afterwardes, to theyr fathers and mothers. For whan the ſoonne or doughter beyng of age, conſyde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth howe the father and mother refuſed labour wyth hym or her <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> put theim oute to nurſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theim regardeth theim therafter. And when they be in neceſſite or lacke, thei thinke thei y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> may ſerue theim
<pb facs="tcp:10411:36" rendition="simple:additions"/> lyke maner. That is to ſaye, to thruſte theim oute of dores, and ſende theim to ſome hoſpytall to findyng, as they did theim. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this, yf the mother were of a good diſpoſicion of bodye and of a verteouſe inclinacyon, there is cauſe geuen to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> childe to grudge agaynſte the mother and father, thinkyng that by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vyce of theim he dranke or ſucked malicyouſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, with the mylke of his nurſe being of a farre worſe diſpoſicion then the mother was. So nowe yf the naturall mother noriſhed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> childe, you ſe what commodityes ſhould folowe. The father ſhuld be ſure that in his lyfe tyme and after his death the mother ſhulde be good to his chyldren &amp; louing. lyke a trewe &amp; a naturall mother, and alſo bothe the father and mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:10411:37"/> ſhoulde be ſure in theyr age, and alwaies y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> the children ſhould haue theim in muche loue feare &amp; reuerence, as trewe children. Alſo the mother beyng nurſe to youre chyld of a good deſpoſicion &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perauncie of bodye and in minde conſtaunt, deuoute and of a good inclinacion ſuche as I truſt your good iudgemente and dyſcrecion wolde choſe, you maye bee ſure, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> youre childe ſhall haue bothe ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue and good temperaunce of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, whiche he may lightely lacke being noriſhed of a ſtraunge wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. So for all theſe cauſes and other that maye be conſidered, I beſeche you folowe that which by theſe reaſons you maye perceyue to be beſte.</p>
               <p>When your childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can ſpeake and vnderſtande, forthwith with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute
<pb facs="tcp:10411:37"/> any delaye put theim vnder ſome vertuouſe perſone to learne to reade and write togethers, but ſpecially to learne vertuouſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners and to ſerue God. And that he may ſo doo from the tyme that he can ſpeake, teache hym euery daye ſome ſhort prayer according to the capacite of his witte or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morye. And as he dothe encreaſe in ſtrength, fede hym with longer prayers, and other fruitefull leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons moſte worthy memory. And thus do with as faire meanes as you may. As for great chaſtiſing and ouer muche feare in teaching yonge childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is not beſt after my iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, for by that the ſpirytes and wittes of children be dulled &amp; being induced by ouermuch feare in youthe, are neuer afterwardes bolde, nor maye lifte vp their min<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des
<pb facs="tcp:10411:38"/> and hertes to thinges of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure, that is to ſaye, thynges of ghoſtely ſtrength and vertue, but are alwayes deiecte, pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſhe, with oute corage or ſtomake to good &amp; honeſt thinges. They doo rather applye theim ſelues afterwarde, when they haue lybertee, to euell then to goodneſſe, which bringig vp is naturall &amp; proper to theym that be borne in bondage and to captiues, and not of fre mens chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren, wherfore both you and your childrens mayſter ſhoulde entice and allure your chyldre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with loue and good wordes. Yea, and then amonge with ſmall giftes to ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and learning, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with feare and force, you ſhoulde boſte and fauoure theym very muche for any lytell thyng that they doo well and conueniently, that by it,
<pb facs="tcp:10411:38"/> they maye haue corage and herte to doo more ſo, yet I doo not vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly diſſwade, but that feare and correccion is neceſſary, ſo it be mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derate in conuenient time and for a notable cauſe. I woulde there were ſhewed to the childe bothe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apple and the rodde, but more of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tener y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apple, and more exhorted to deſerue the rewarde and praiſe then the correccyon. And all the tyme that youre childe is in your houſe frome ſchole, kepe hym al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes with you in youre preſence as nygh as you can. And let hym take his meate at your table, and lye in youre chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber. For of your maners and behaueoure at the ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble and chaumber, he ſhall ſee &amp; heare better communicacyon and learne mo vertuoſe maners, here more wyſdome, and take hede of
<pb facs="tcp:10411:39"/> more ciuilytee or nurture then in the kechin or ſtable amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt your ſeruauntes.</p>
               <p>Haue the preſence of your child in ſuche veneracyon that before God and hym be ſpoken no vici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſe wordes, no ſwearing, no lies no backbiting or ſlaundering, no curſing, mocki<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g, or ribauldry, no wordes of fraude or diſceite. For the childe can ſpeake but ſuche la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gage as he heareth, and bycauſe he is mooſte, yee alwaies lightely in youre conuerſacion he wyll vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter your maners to other folkes. Let hym therfore be ware of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſuche maner of ſpeches. But beware you muche more, for to you it ſhalbe rekened double ſyn, youre owne and youre chyldes, you knowe that of a naturall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinacyon, ſuche woordes as are,
<pb facs="tcp:10411:39"/> ſoundynge vnto euell, are more promptely fixed in theyr myndes then other. And this ſame exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tacion or monicyon ſhoulde be ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen vnto youre chyldes mayſter, (yf he be honeſt, he wyll thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully receiue it) that youre chylde heare nothyng, but that whiche ſoundeth to vertue &amp; goodneſſe.</p>
               <p>And to cauſe that youre childe re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fuſe not youre companye or his maiſters, bothe you and he muſte ſome time fynde your childe ſome pointes and inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes to playe and ſuffer hym to vſe honeſt ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes or playes then amonge, for the recreacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſpirytes, that he maye be the gladder with you, and loue you and hym with reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent dreade the better.</p>
               <p>And ſo ſhall he with a better wyl applie his learning without trem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>beling,
<pb facs="tcp:10411:40"/> feare, or inforce. And after this maner, he ſhall learne more and ſoner. The women children wolde be broughte vp in all feare and drede, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> litle fauoure ſhewed theim vntyll they bee of a perfyte age and vnderſtanding. For as in men is nothing more reproua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble then to be cowardes, fearfull, pekyſhe, and of no ſtomake or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage: So in wemen is the contra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry, in whom there is nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g more laudable then fearefulneſſe and gentylneſſe of ſtomake. To the mother youre wyfe, geue charge to doo her dewtye in bringing vp your women chyldren verteouſly and in the lawe and feare of God as you doo the men children.</p>
               <p>In the choyſe of a mayſter for youre chylde, yf you maye haue one bothe well learned and good
<pb facs="tcp:10411:40"/> and verteous in lyuyng for mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney ſake or coſte: forſake hym not excepte ye loue money better then vertue &amp; learnynge, euery thynge is as it is loued and eſtemed. The wyſe man ſetteth muche by lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynge and honeſte maners, the rude ignoraunte and folyſhe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone ſetteth lytle by theim, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is not acquaynted wyth theim. If he ſhoulde lacke eyther of theſe two thynges learnyng or vertue, better it were y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he lacked parte of the learnyng then of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue. Vertue is more of price then learnyng, for learnynge is but a meane thynge wherby men come to vertue thorough the grace of God. Learnyng is for vertue and not vertue for learnyng. It is bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter to be good and verteous, then learned and worldly wyſe. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:10411:41"/> rather choyſe goodnes &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tue for your chylde and you, then learnynge, yf bothe maye not bee had together:</p>
               <p>Alſo with letters, let your child learne muſike. Alſo let hym w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out hurtyng hym ſelfe learne the vſe of weapons or armes, as buckler plaiynge or ſuche other. The one for recreacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his ſpirites, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the ſtrength of his bodye It ſhall make hym hable &amp; bolde ſo that in peace and warre (yf he ſhould be inforced therto) w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel and ſtrength he may preuaile. And ioyntly with this he ſhoulde not be ignoraunte of thynges ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarye to his lyuynge, wherfore euen fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his yong age, he ſhoulde haue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> knowledge of the moneye that is vſed &amp; of the valewe of it. And for this it ſhalbe good to put
<pb facs="tcp:10411:41"/> ſome in his power, &amp; to make him buy al thynges neceſſarye for his owne weryng, from cappe to ſhoe, at the fyrſte &amp; ſeconde tyme wyth helpe of other, &amp; afterwardes by hym ſelfe. And after to putte hym in buſines of greater charge, with greater ſummes of moneye, &amp; let hym vſe of parte after his owne diſcrecion, makynge (when you ſhall cal hym) accompte to you of the beſtowyng. The commen vſe as me ſemeth may not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, which is, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> men for the moſte parte wyll not truſte theyr childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with any of theyr ſubſtaunce, nor let theim knowe nor ſca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tely vnder ſtande y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> valewe of money, which thyng cauſeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> afterwardes whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they enheryte theyr fathers good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, they ſpende all vndiſcreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye as they that knowe not, what
<pb facs="tcp:10411:42"/> it is, nor the valewe of that they enherite. The cauſe is that the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wyll leaue all to his ſonne af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter his death and in his lyfe tyme nothyng. But if after the maner aboue reherſed ye vſe your childe he ſhall not onelye for lacke of knowlage myſpende his enhery<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, but ſhalbe more able wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer he become to geue a reke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng for hym ſelfe, and as it is co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>menly ſayde, ſhalbe able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany with men and to helpe hym ſelfe hauyng knowlage of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> thyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges neceſſary for his lyuynge. Yf he ſhoulde myſpende any thynge it were beter he dyd it in your pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſence, where by good admonicion and councel he maye be amended &amp; corrected, then after your death when the moſte parte of folkes (to haue parte of his exſpences) wyll
<pb facs="tcp:10411:42"/> prayſe hym in his lewde ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng rather then w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> counſell monyſhe hym, ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de or correcte hym, nowe ye maye wyth a lytle porcyon of your goodes knowe the proofe of your chyld in your life, and in ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner be ſure that he ſhal wel mayn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teyne and diſpoſe that you leaue hym afterwardes whan you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gone. And ſeynge I ſpeake of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſynge or diſtrybutyng of goo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des by youre chylde, ye oughte to entyce hym from hys chyld<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hode or infancye (yf it might bee) to haue compaſſion vpon y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> poore and to vſe to geue ſome almes, yea for to inſtructe hym, whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer almes you or your wyfe dooe geue, let it be geuen by his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des or your other chyldren yf they be in the waye or preſente with you at y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> tyme. This do you oftetimes
<pb facs="tcp:10411:43"/> not onely to inſtructe your chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but becauſe God ſo inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth you that by youre example &amp; vſe of it he may learne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his ten dre age euer to helpe the nedye &amp; poore, yf he be of habylitee, yf no, yet he may learne to bee deuoute mercyfull, and pytiefull. But re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> in this thyng, and in al other goodnes. Lykewyſe y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cypall exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of vertue profytyng your chylde muſte come of youre good example, which he ſeeth you to do and ſhewe. For nothynge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his maiſter or other perſones ſhal do or ſhewe hym, can ſtycke or be ſo fyxed in his mynde as youre wordes and dedes. Nowe then yf you bryng vp youre chylde after this maner as is here layd before your eyes, there is no doubte, but he ſhalbe a good manne. Vpon
<pb facs="tcp:10411:43"/> whiche grounde or foundacion, whether he be enclyned to bee of the clergye or of the other ſorte of men, called laye men, whether he woulde be a preaſt, alwayes a ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheler or a maryed manne, he ſhalbe an honeſte manne. But yf he be dyſpoſed to be of the clergy, one thyng I woulde you counce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led hym, that in no wyſe, he make any maner vowe, nor profeſſyon vntyll he bee thyrtye or nyghe to thyrtye yeares of age. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that tyme or nyghe aboute that tyme, none doeth wel knowe hym ſelfe. Happy is he that doeth then. To ſaye truthe, it is harde for me here to appoynte hym any tyme, his owne faythe and loue whiche he hathe receyued of God muſte bynde hym hereto, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brynge that when Peter promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb facs="tcp:10411:44"/> vpon his owne ſtrengthe he could not perfourme his promiſe but afterwardes when he promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he loued his may<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Chriſt, ſaiyng: Lord y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt that I loue the, he was ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge So in what rype age ſoeuer your chylde be, and woulde make vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes or promyſes to take other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion then he receyued at Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome (an hygher or perfygh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter vowe he can not make.) But yf he would promyſe the vowe of chaſtytee, the whyche vowe all Chriſten menne and women haue profeſſed, becauſe they haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed Chriſte, whatſoeuer order of lyuyng any perſone chriſtened doeth profeſſe, he profeſſeth chaſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tee euen though he entre into ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trymonye as is aboue ſayde. But yf he be diſpoſed to liue ſole
<pb facs="tcp:10411:44"/> &amp; chaſte, it maye not come of hym ſelfe, for it paſſeth mannes infyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite. But doubtleſſe if he miſtruſt his owne ſtrengthe, and thinke &amp; beleue verely, that by the power and might of Chriſte, and confy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in hym, ſo that he may ſaye with a ſtronge beleue. All thinges are poſſyble vnto the beleuer, and thynke verely that by Chriſte he hath and ſhall ouercome y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> world thinkig on Chriſtes worde, which ſaieth, truſte ye, or haue you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fydence, for I haue ouercome the worlde, lette hym thinke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he may do all thinges through hym that comforteth. In hym then and for hym, lette youre chylde make his vowe, if he be ſo diſpoſed, &amp; doubt leſſe hauyng ſuche, and the ſame ſtaffe to leane to, he ſhal not fayle We heare of too manye, whiche
<pb facs="tcp:10411:45"/> for theyr belies ſakes, or for their frendes pleaſures onely, whiche are men, haue made their vowes, and be had in deriſyon of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> world for the breaking of theim no won<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der that they ſlyde whiche buylde vpon manne.</p>
               <p>Lette youre chylde buylde v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon God, and he ſhall ſtande. For God is able to make hym ſtande And he wyll dooe all thyng vnto theim that beleue in hym. Warne hym thanne that what ſoeuer he doothe, he dooe it in the name of God wyth beleue, that God will dooe for hym vnto his owne glorye.</p>
               <p>If ye miſtruſt hym not, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your child is aboute .xxx. yeres of age, he ſhall haue a good iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of hym ſelfe. No man knoweth per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyghtelye his owne ſtrengthe, yet
<pb facs="tcp:10411:45"/> at that age, by youre good endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing, he ſhall knowe and perceiue what Chriſte wylleth hym in the Goſpell, and ſoo thoroughe the worde of God and good reaſon, whiche he is lyke to haue at that age, maye be bolde after Goddes worde to iudge of hym ſelfe, but chyefely and princypally exhorte hym to kepe the vowe and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe whiche he made at the fonte of Baptyſme, that he renounced and vtterly dyd forſake the deuel and all his workes &amp; all his pom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pes, yf he tarye onelye vpon theſe vowes, he ſhalbe ſuer to be a good chriſtyan manne.</p>
               <p>If he beleue in God, the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in Chriſte the ſonne, and in the hooly ghooſte, thre in parſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, yet one God in eſſence.</p>
               <p>To beleue in God, is to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit all
<pb facs="tcp:10411:46"/> oure whole herte vnto hym, oure thoughtes, wordes, and workes. If he thus beleue, doubteleſſe he ſhalbe ſaued from ſinne, from the deuill and from hell and the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting death thoroughe Chriſtes death, by whome he is deed to the worlde and liueth to God, and by whome he ſhalbe defe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded againſt the deuell and the vnclenneſſe of his owne fleſhe and all wycked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. He nowe hauyng this loue and charytee to God thoroughe Chriſte, is ſuer a good chriſtyan man. What profeſſion can make a manne better? I would to God that other profeſſyons hadde not made men wourſe. This vowe of Baptiſme exhorte your ſoonne to kepe, whiche he hath made all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, and hathe bounde hym ſelfe to the obſeruaunce thereof by ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reties,
<pb facs="tcp:10411:46"/> at whiche alſo were bound with hym his godfathers &amp; god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothers. It might be thought to be lytl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſcrecion or no good cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cell to bind him ſelfe (as he might be perſwaded to vowes of greate perfeccion) not diligentlye ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng to accompliſhe the vowe that he hathe made all redye. What a wyſe man is he, that wyll ſeke an heuyer burthen, when he percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth that he is to weake to beare a lighter? Induce hym, that he earneſtly and hartely deſyre God of his grace, to dooe that whiche Chriſte willeth hym, and to haue hym in his remembraunce, with vnfayned loue &amp; reuerent dreade where ſoeuer he be goyng, ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, riding, or reſting. And lette hym beleue that Chriſt is of ſuch gentilneſſe and goodneſſe, that he
<pb facs="tcp:10411:47"/> may haue hym to dwel with hym euen in the inwarde chaumber of his breſt, yf he wolde doo ſo much for his ſake, as to expell Sathan with his felowes. God the father of his plenteous goodneſſe and Chriſte his ſonne naturall of his mere pitee and mercye thoroughe the worke of the holy ghooſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding frome theim bothe whiche thre: The father, the ſonne and ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly ghoſt is one God, wyl be at one with your ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne, yf he wyl ſeke his fauoure by learning keping &amp; fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing his holy worde. I wolde you wold ſay often times to hym, that he ſhoulde be a good, a iuſte and a perfyte chriſten man. If he coulde beleue certaynly y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſte were geuen vnto hym for his ſyn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, but this canne he not beleue
<pb facs="tcp:10411:47"/> with a corrupte conſcyence.</p>
               <p>If youre ſonne be not diſpoſed to be of the clergye, but of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſorte (called laye menne) he maye not be of the worlde and a good chriſtian manne togethers. Fauoure him with continual cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cell &amp; reparte of ſuche goodes as God hathe ſente you, as is afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayde, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> in youre dayes you maye ſee hym profete, and be an honeſt manne, vnto youre greate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte: whiche comforte they lac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that wyll not reparte of their goodes vnto theyr chyldren vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyll they dye.</p>
               <p>Wherfore theyr chyldren mighte thynke that they were the leſſe bounde vnto theym by a greate deale. Conſydering that perforce they muſte leaue it behinde theim If they myghte kepe it ſtyll, they
<pb facs="tcp:10411:48"/> wolde. It is a ſmall benefite then of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> father, whiche perforce ſhuld leaue it to other, leaueth it to his childe. Seing that yf he dyd the contrary, he ſhoulde put his ſoule in greate ieopardy, for the defrau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng of his chylde of theſe thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges whiche Goddes lawe and na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture wolde to be his. Wherfore my louyng frende, thoughe you had ſome certayne preſumpcions that your childe wolde ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nde his porcyon of ſubſtaunce euell, take not his ryght from hym. Better it ſhalbe for youre ſoule y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> he ſpende it euell, then peraduenture an other wolde ſpende it well. This maye nowe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyſe, as touching your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10411:48"/>
               <head>¶ The gouernaunce or orderyng of exſpences in the houſe.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the reſte, to ſpeake of exſpences in the houſe, ſee that youre dayly exſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces be ſo moderated, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ye may egually and iuſtely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinue with out ryot, or ſo greate welfare that it might not endure, or withoute puttyng your ſelfe in neceſſyte or nede or grudge of mynde for the largenes of the exſpences, or that your houſhold ſhould grudge for your ſtraytnes or nygardſhpppe. Therfore the order that you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynne kepe conſtantelye, for any lytle exceſſe dayly vſed, in proceſſe of tyme groweth to greate ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes. The vitayles for your table ſhould be ſuche as ye finde moſte conuenient for your health, of the
<pb facs="tcp:10411:49"/> whiche beware of greate dyuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, for the dyuerſytee of meates engendereth diuerſytiees of ſyke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes. As for the quantitee, as I would not that you did defraude nature with takynge to lytle, ſo I woulde you to thynke that ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluytee of meate and drinke, is the vtter deſtruccion of nature, loue ſymple or ſyngle meates, they be ſimple that be not mengeled with many dyuerſe thynges or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded with many dyuerſe kyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des of fleſhes, and wyth theim. And with dyuerſe fruytes and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe kyndes of ſpyces, and all theſe in one dyſhe. And lykewyſe ſome vſe dyuerſe kyndes of dryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, whiche all withoute doubte decayeth health, thoughe it be not by and by felt or perceyued, but in proceſſe of tyme they wyl vtter
<pb facs="tcp:10411:49"/> the ſelues, &amp; bryng forth death or deathes brother. For of this it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth that together in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth the feuers, the head ache, the tothe ache, the goute, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> bely ache, the ſtranguyllia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and other diſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes out of noumbre, whiche I can not reherſe. Wher though of one maner of meate ſurfet were vſed, or of one maner of drynke, a man ſhuld haue but one maner of theſe ſickeneſſe or diſeaſes or none at al yf the exceſſe wer not great, where throughe yf you neede the vſe of medecynes, I would with the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſell of ſome learned &amp; good phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion, you vſed ſymple medycines as nighe as wer poſſible, fleyng y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> compoſicio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of many drogeries, &amp; not onelye ſymple but to take of ſuche medecynes as are of herbe rootes or fruytes of this ſame lande beynge proued for good,
<pb facs="tcp:10411:50"/> rather then of ſuche drogeryes that are brought out of the lande I thynke not, but yf our phyſycy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were ſo diligente and labory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous to ſeke theſame thynges that God and nature hath geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medyes as the phiſycions were y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> wrote, whom they folowe partely whiche becauſe they were experte in natural thynges, wrote of theſe drogeryes that groweth in Affri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca, Syrya &amp; Grecia, they woulde not muche vſe of theſe drogeryes whiche are in other countreyes, but ſuche as God ſendeth for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medyes in euery lande, whereby they ſhoulde fynde more naturall remedyes for mannes health.</p>
               <p>As concernyng the other parte of your houſholde or gouernau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce therof (I meane your ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes) I wold you had no mo ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes
<pb facs="tcp:10411:50"/> in your houſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ye maye kepe oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cupied, and y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> none eat their bread in ydelnes, but that they haue la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour with meate, and meate with laboure. For as it is crueltye to cauſe ſeruauntes to laboure with out meate, ſo it is veraye noyfull or hurtefull to geue ſeruauntes meate without labour. For it ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth theym lumpyſhe, luſkyſhe drowſye and ſlouthfull, vycyous, lecherous and glotons. One ydle ſeruaunte wyll lyghtlye corrupte al the houſhold. If ye haue a true ſeruaunte &amp; a faythfull, loue hym as youre ſonne, let hym knowe your fauoure, that he may bee an example to his felowes. In theyr clothyng and feedynge, let theim vſe a meane withoute any exceſſe, that is, that the clothynge bee not fyne nor curyouſlye made, but
<pb facs="tcp:10411:51"/> courſe and ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to kepe theim from colde. And the meate in no wyſe delycate, but groſſe, ſuche as wil ſuffice to kepe theim in health and from houngre. Paye them truely theyr wages without dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion or brydgyng, let theim fynde your wyll more prone and redyer to paye theim, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you fynd theim to labour for it: yee yf it be ſo paye them w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſame quyppe or note. But in the meane tyme prouoke theim with many fayre ſpeaches, to do their dutie, yet not alwayes ſo, remembryng that an eaſy and a gentle medycyne healeth not al ſores, nor y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> flaterynge inſtygacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, maketh not the horſſe go ſtyll: ſometymes the ſpore muſt be vſed excepte the corage be very luſtye, lyuelye and quycke. To make an ende, let God and reaſon rule you
<pb facs="tcp:10411:51"/> and after theim rule youre wyfe and houſholde.</p>
               <p>Theſe counſelles I would you vſed for youre owne wealth &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtee, thynkyng that there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyng better then good counſell. See therfore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> by the euyll coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the deuyll, ye ſuffre no euell cogitacions to engendre and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe in your herte, for they wyll brynge forthe death, not tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall or bodelye death, but death euerlaſtyng. From which Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus our ſauyoure ſaue you in whome lyue &amp; reigne by purenes of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oute end. <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10411:52"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:10411:52"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:10411:53"/>
               <head>¶ This treatyſe folowynge, I haue written out of a great clerke S. Barnarde, in ſome places leauyng his order becauſe of ſhortnes.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Owe my dere belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued frend, theſe fore ſayde leſſons well marked, I truſte ye wyll fyrſt aboue all thynges order your ſelfe to our Lorde, ſeakyng aboue and before all thynges the kyng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, in guydyng your houſholde and orderynge youre gooddes, whiche alwayes thynke to haue receyued of God to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noure hym in his poore and nedy perſones. And for his honoure ſe that peace be in your houſe, and y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al yours agree together with you
<pb facs="tcp:10411:53"/> or elles all youre goodes maye &amp; wyll ſone come to nought. A reche<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſſe perſone may ſone ſet on fire, waſte and deſtroie greate goodes Haue therfore a good ſight or eye vnto the laboures of your ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes, for vnder theym youre ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce maye ſoone be waſted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you knowe of it, if your good<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des beginne to waſte or diminiſhe forthwith diminyſhe youre char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges. For who that ſpendeth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yonde his facultye, no wonder, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nede thoughe he greued be. It is good prouydence ofte tymes to compte and compare your good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and gaines with your erſpen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces. Ofte tymes to ouerſe youre goodes ſhalbe very good, remem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bring, that the eye of the mayſter maketh a fatte horſe, and the ſtep of the huſbande a fatte dungehil,
<pb facs="tcp:10411:54"/> that is the maiſters preſence pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiteth much, bie peace w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſuffering and you ſhalbe ſure of it. Thynke coſte made vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> riotouſe perſones to be vtterly loſte, not ſo vpon kin and frendes &amp; poore perſones Se y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> you charge your ſonnes dough<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ters and ſeruauntes to flee gloto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. For y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t once made a glo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ton, wyl neuer ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de his maners Glotony is filthy, reprouable and ſtinking, &amp; will make the vſers of it ſoone rotten, and ſhorte lyued. Meane feading with ſcarſytie, or withoute full belye that is riſyng frome meate with an appetyte to eate, profiteth muche bothe to the ſoule and bodye. Thinke that the vſe of delycate foode, wyll ſoone marre a good ſeruaunt, as of riot and waſtfulneſſe. Beware of ny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gardie, for as riot is a foliſhe and
<pb facs="tcp:10411:54"/> vndyſcrete waſte of the gyftes of god, ſo nigardie is a fooliſhe and a nedeleſſe feare, the myſtruſte of God, &amp; a liuyng euer in pouertee an heapi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vp of goodes, for who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> none ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tel. Be therfore a maiſter ouer your goodes, haue theim for your ſelfe and other, not for your heires onely. Feare and loue god and feare hym duely, and thynke that fiſhes, foules, beaſtes &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes be fedde of his liberalytee, &amp; ſhall you then periſhe for lacke If you wiſhe for derth, you wiſhe for y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> derth of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> poore. Sell better cheape at home the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mune market, better cheape to your ene<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mye then to other ſtraungers, for by a kind dede, he wil be better o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>med then by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſweard. Be ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer at debate w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your neighbours ſtudy to bring theim at one y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſo be
<pb facs="tcp:10411:55"/> The loue of youre neyghboures is a ſurer warde, then a caſtel thre double walled. A gentyll minde &amp; a noble herte wyll not greatlye be troubeled with wemens bablyng ſpeche or thretenyng: ſmilyng, or laughyng, wyll ſoner correcte a ſhrewe, then ſharpe ſtrokes and y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſtaffe. Wemen may be kept good with gentyll entreatye, they maye not knowe that they be ſuſpecte, but euer muſte be cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſayled with louyng maner. An olde woman vncleane of liuyng, were worthye to be buried quicke. For ſhe is not only dead before God, but killeth other. A woman that hath a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient apparell, to deſire chaunge, is a token of lytel wit or ſadneſſe. A coſtely veſture aboue the ſtate or degree of the perſone is a ſigne of lightneſſe. Truſte hym rather
<pb facs="tcp:10411:55"/> for youre frende that dothe ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what for you, then hym that ſayth I am youres, in all that I can &amp; maye doo. In wordes you ſhall fynde greate plentye of frendes, a trewe frende loueth at all tymes and neuer fayleth at nede. Riches maye not be compared to a faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full frende, when you geue coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell ſaye, thus ſemeth to me beſte, not thus you muſte nedes do, leſt you might rather gette blame for youre councell then thanke, yf it ſpede not well. If geſters Ioug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, or minſtrelles come to youre houſe, ſaye that you haue no lod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging for theym, or for ſuche ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoures. If you be once delighted in their vncomely paſtymes, they wyll appoint you anone to be ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ried to an other wife, whoſe name is pouertee or beggere, choſe you
<pb facs="tcp:10411:56"/> whether, yf it chaunce you to bee where as they be, I aduiſe you to make wiſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you herde theim not, nor ſet by theyr vnchriſtenlyke pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtymes: For yf they perceyue you but once to laughe, they wyll take it for an earneſt to crye largeſſe, &amp; to haue rewarde, wherfore haue not muche to doo with the galow clappers. God is not well pleaſed with that occupacion whileſt they be miniſters to ſynne, and vſe ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wordes. If you haue a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt of an highe proude mynde and ſtoborne ſtomake (leſte he do you and youres harme) put hym away, ſo doo him y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> doeth alwaies (ſpecialli to your face) praiſe your maners. Thynke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> flaterers and liers be to trewe men enemyes, as they be to y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> treweth which is god Euer ſuſpect the flaterer, &amp; thinke
<pb facs="tcp:10411:56"/> that he ſpeaketh to deceyue bothe hym ſelfe &amp; you. Make your buil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dinges rather for nede then plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, leſte for your pleaſures ſake God wyll not longe ſuffer you to take profyte of theim. The deſire of building for pleſure wyl neuer haue ende, vntyll pouertee teache witte ſomwhat to late. If you bee compelled to ſell your landes, ſell theim not to greate perſones, but rather for leſſe, to men of lower e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate. Better it is to ſell, then to borowe by vſury, for vſury maye cauſe you to vſe this worlde glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryouſly. It wyll ſhitte you cleane frome the glorye of God. If you bye a bargayne, be not checke fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe with great ſtates. Dewe te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraunce in an houſhold is a thig of an highe prayſe, let your wyne rather then ale or bere be holſome
<pb facs="tcp:10411:57"/> and temperate. Stronge drinkes maketh weake braynes, and feble to be knowen. Sobre drynke is helthfull bothe to body and ſoule And the ſober wyll be contente w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> lytle drinke ſmal and quicke, who that amonge much ſtrong drinke is ſobre &amp; not troubled in brayne, maye be called a God vpon earth Wreſtle not with it yf you doo by my councel, leſte you catche a fall If it ſhoulde happen to trouble your brayne, gette you out of com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>panye to ſadneſſe and ſorowe yf you wyll not be vtterly aſhamed before menne. Before God howe youre conſcience ſhall iudge you it is not in me to iudge, who that by wordes wolde excuſe his dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kenneſſe, declareth his owne diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe. The vſe of wyne belongeth not to yonge perſones. Beware of
<pb facs="tcp:10411:57"/> dronken ſurgynes or phiſycions lewde and ignoraunt, let hym not learne in you to heale other.</p>
               <p>Hawkes and hou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des do ſpend more then they do get. I dell per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons may haue theim to ſet theim ſelues a worke to leſe time, fooles and neglygent perſones and care<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſſe haue many miſfortunes, and therefore they accuſe and blame fortune, whiche is not to be bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, for it is her nature to deceiue whom wyſedome, diſcrecion, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light &amp; learnyng doth not lyght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye blame, dilygent warenes and a good foreſyght be no company<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to myſfortune, but myſfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, negligence &amp; ſlothe be light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neuer aſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, they be cater cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyns. The ſluggarde ſayth, God wyll helpe. Yet wyll not he begyn to helpe hym ſelfe. I maye ſaye to
<pb facs="tcp:10411:58"/> hym, that God geueth all thyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, but yet geueth he not to the, the bull by the horne. Sette thy hande to the carte, and God wyll it vp pull. The wyſe man ſendeth the ſludgarde for example vnto y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> pyſmyer or aunte to learne to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure. For a man is borne to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boure, and the byrde to flye. He y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> laboureth not, is not worthy to eat. Let fewe or none ydell perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s therfore be in your houſe, &amp; take good hede to euery one of theim, ſpecyally that they can ſaye, oure Chriſten beleue, called the Crede, and our Lordes prayer called the Pater noſter, with the Aue Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria, and the commaundementes of God. And at euery dyner and ſupper let one of youre houſholde eyther ſay by herte or vpon booke theſame, that other maye learne
<pb facs="tcp:10411:58"/> and that they that haue learned maye kepe theim in memorye. If there be any obſtinate perſone or other, that hath openly offended, let hym be openly puniſhed to the exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of other, yf y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſone be of a tendre age w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> a ſherpe rodde. If he be of further age, let hym eate courſer meate then hys felowes &amp; that in the myddel of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> hall vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſtole by him ſelf, or other ſuch like rebuke or ſhame let hym ſuffre, and feare not to correcte vice, leſt Goddes puniſhemente wyll cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recte you, but correcte for loue and not vengeaunce. Then ſhall youre ſeruauntes loue you, and blame theimſelues and learne to hate ſynnes and offences.</p>
               <p>Spe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d as you get, it is no good huſbandrye to borowe when you waxe olde, &amp; at al times truſt God
<pb facs="tcp:10411:59" rendition="simple:additions"/> better then chyldren or frendes, That you ſende before you, you muſte nedes fynde. Heauen is a ſurer keper of treaſures then any cofer, caſtell or towre. Thynke then when y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> poore profereth forth his hand, that God appoſeth you what you wolde doo for hym, and of the goodes that you leaue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hynde you, appoynte euerye per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone his parte. It were better to leaue nothyng, then that ſtryfe &amp; Goddes dyſpleaſure: ſhoulde be lefte amonge youres, for youre goodes. Truſte theim beſte, that beſte loue theyr owne ſowles.</p>
               <p>Not theim that wyl ſay that they wyll doo for youre ſoule.</p>
               <p>Make youre Teſtamente eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry yere, or elles as occaſyon ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be geuen alter it, and lay it, wher when nede is, it maye be founde.
<pb facs="tcp:10411:59" rendition="simple:additions"/> No man is ſure howe to ende his lyfe or when, but well to ende his lyfe, or to dye well, is well to liue, whiche he graunte you and me, and other beleuing people that boughte vs, oure Lorde Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſte oure ſauioure redemer, feder, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender, in whome lyue you and reygne worlde without ende thorough his grace and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye.</p>
               <closer>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men.</closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:10411:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>
                  <figure/>
               </p>
               <pb facs="tcp:10411:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
